# Ruhama Yared

Full Stack Software Engineer | (571) 340.7028 | ruhamayared1@gmail.com | Alexandria, VA | LinkedIn | GitHub

#### **About Me**

I am a software engineer with a unique combination of experience in both front-end and back-end development, utilizing primarily JavaScript and Python. I am passionate about creating intuitive and user-friendly software that enhances the user experience. My background as a high school math teacher, with over 10 years of experience in designing course content, training materials, and instructional videos, brings a unique perspective to problem-solving and an exceptional ability to communicate technical concepts to non-technical stakeholders. My strengths in project management and attention to detail, coupled with my eagerness to continuously learn and stay up-to-date with the latest technologies, make me a valuable asset to any team. I am passionate about continuing to learn and master the craft of software engineering and am seeking roles at a company where I can learn, grow, and make an impact.

#### **Skills**

Languages - JavaScript, HTML, CSS, Python | Libraries and Frameworks - React, Node.js, Express.js, jQuery Database - MongoDB, Mongoose | Other - Responsive Web Design, RESTful APIs, GitHub, Slack, Trello, VSCode, Render

### **Software Development Projects**

09/2022 - Present

Polynomials App - Full-stack application that allows users to view, create, read, and update polynomials as well as user comments

- Developed a full-stack web application using Node.js, Express, and MongoDB, which allows users to create, edit, and delete polynomials
- Implemented RESTful API calls to an Express, MongoDB, Node.js backend, handling all CRUD operations and thoroughly testing all backend routes during development using Postman
- Used Mongoose to define schemas for MongoDB collections, ensuring data integrity and consistency
- Leveraged Embedded JavaScript (EJS) and JavaScript methods and functions to create a RESTful API and improve the functionality of the application
- Styled the application using HTML5 and CSS flexbox layout, resulting in a visually pleasing and responsive design that adapts to different devices and screen sizes

What's there to Drink? - A web application that displays cocktail information for a fun night using The Cocktail DB API

- Designed and developed a web application using Vanilla JavaScript, jQuery, CSS3, and HTML5 to organize and display the visual aspects of the application, resulting in an aesthetically pleasing and user-friendly interface
- Utilized wireframing and UI planning techniques, including mobile application and markup language, to create a clear and effective design for the application
- Leveraged Git and GitHub throughout the development process, committing frequently and deploying the application successfully
- Implemented JavaScript methods and functions to retrieve and manipulate data from a public API, resulting in a dynamic and interactive user experience

#### **Professional Experience**

Fairfax County Public Schools, Alexandria, VA | Mathematics Teacher Alexandria City Public Schools, Alexandria, VA | Mathematics Teacher Nysmith School for the Gifted, Herndon, VA | Mathematics Teacher

08/2021 - Present 08/2019 - 06/2020 08/2014 - 06/2017

- Coached and onboarded peers to new Learning Management Systems (LMS) to integrate with modern processes and improve workflow efficiency
- Collaborated with cross-functional teams to address collective challenges, and discussed and implemented new research and technologies, resulting in a noticeable enhancement of student engagement
- Curated over 100+ supplemental resources that met organizational and technical specifications and accessibility standards, resulting in improved student fluency and test scores
- Developed and implemented project-based formal assessments to evaluate learner progress and areas for growth, resulting in 100% pass rate for state standardized tests in 2021
- Communicated with stakeholders and provided weekly announcements through LMS, calls, and emails, resulting in significantly improved parent and stakeholder engagement
- Utilized instructional design methods such as PADDIE, Inquiry Based, Backwards Design, and PBL, resulting in improved student learning and retention
- Led curriculum development and instructional design teams utilizing technology, including evaluating and selecting online resources, to improve efficiency and align with organizational goals.

#### The Presidential Precinct, Charlottesville, VA | Program Summer Fellow

06/2018 - 08/2018

Planned and implemented projects to provide day-to-day academic, cross-cultural, and social support

• Supported six-week Civic Leadership Institute for 25 emerging leaders from Sub-Saharan Africa

#### Education

## General Assembly | Remote

Software Engineering Immersive

2022 - 2023

Full-stack software engineering immersive student in an intensive, twenty-four-week, 450+ hour program focused on product development fundamentals, object-oriented programming, MVC frameworks, data modeling, and team collaboration strategies. Developed a portfolio of individual and group projects.

## University of Virginia | Charlottesville, VA

Master of Public Policy 2017 - 2019

Thesis: Ensuring Equity in Academic Achievement for Young Girls of Color via Positive Identity Development

#### Goucher College | Baltimore, MD

Bachelor of Arts in Education, Mathematics

2009 - 2013